<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss version='2.0' xmlns:atom='http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom'>
<channel>
<atom:link href='http://clojuredatascience.com/' rel='self' type='application/rss+xml'/>
<title>
Clojure for Data Science
</title>
<link>
http://clojuredatascience.com/
</link>
<description>
This is the blog to accompany the book Clojure for Data Science published by Packt.
</description>
<lastBuildDate>
Sat, 05 Sep 2015 15:19:19 +0100
</lastBuildDate>
<generator>
clj-rss
</generator>
<item>
<guid>
http://clojuredatascience.com/posts/2015-09-05-published.html
</guid>
<link>
http://clojuredatascience.com/posts/2015-09-05-published.html
</link>
<title>
Published!
</title>
<description>
&lt;p&gt;It's been over a year after I began writing &lt;a href='https://www.packtpub.com/big-data-and-business-intelligence/clojure-data-science'&gt;Clojure for Data Science&lt;/a&gt; and I'm thrilled to say that the book is finally published. You can pick up a copy from &lt;a href='https://www.packtpub.com/big-data-and-business-intelligence/clojure-data-science'&gt;the publisher's website&lt;/a&gt; or from &lt;a href='http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/1784397180/ref=as&amp;#95;li&amp;#95;tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1634&amp;creative=19450&amp;creativeASIN=1784397180&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=henrygarnerco-21'&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Anyone who has written a book will know that it is no small undertaking (I ought to have applied my usual &quot;multiply by 3&quot; rule of code estimation to the project at the outset). Many people have contributed along the way.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I'm grateful to &lt;a href='https://twitter.com/econohammer'&gt;Dan Hammer&lt;/a&gt;, my Packt reviewer, for his valuable perspective as a practicing data scientist, and to those other brave souls who patiently read through the very rough early (and not-so-early) drafts. Foremost among these are &lt;a href='https://twitter.com/EleonoreMayola'&gt;Éléonore Mayola&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href='https://twitter.com/paulrabutcher'&gt;Paul Butcher&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href='https://twitter.com/derbex'&gt;Jeremy Hoyland&lt;/a&gt;. Your feedback was not always easy to hear, but it made the book so much better than it would otherwise have been.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thank you to the wonderful team at &lt;a href='http://www.mastodonc.com/'&gt;MastodonC&lt;/a&gt; who tackled a pre-release version of this book in their company book club, especially &lt;a href='https://twitter.com/EleonoreMayola'&gt;Éléonore Mayola&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href='https://twitter.com/jasonbelldata'&gt;Jase Bell&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href='https://twitter.com/elise&amp;#95;huard'&gt;Elise Huard&lt;/a&gt;. I'm grateful to &lt;a href='https://twitter.com/fhr'&gt;Francine Bennett&lt;/a&gt; for her advice early on—which helped to shape the structure of the book—and also to &lt;a href='https://twitter.com/otfrom'&gt;Bruce Durling&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href='https://twitter.com/sw1nn'&gt;Neale Swinnerton&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href='https://twitter.com/mrchrisadams'&gt;Chris Adams&lt;/a&gt; for their company during the otherwise lonely weekends spent writing in the office.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thank you to my friends from the machine learning study group: &lt;a href='https://twitter.com/tansakuu'&gt;Sam Joseph&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href='https://twitter.com/galfridus'&gt;Geoff Hogg&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href='https://twitter.com/bewt85'&gt;Ben Taylor&lt;/a&gt; for reading the early drafts and providing feedback suitable for Clojure newcomers; and also to &lt;a href='https://twitter.com/snapington'&gt;Luke Snape&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href='https://twitter.com/tcoupland'&gt;Tom Coupland&lt;/a&gt; of the &lt;a href='https://twitter.com/BristolClojure'&gt;Bristol Clojurians&lt;/a&gt; for providing the opportunity to test the material out on its intended audience.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A heartfelt thanks to my dad, Nicholas, for interpreting my vague scribbles into the fantastic figures you see in this book, and to my mum, Jacqueline, and sister, Mary, for being such patient listeners in the times I felt like thinking aloud. Last, but by no means least, thank you to the Nuggets of Wynford Road, Russell and Wendy, for the tea and sympathy whenever it occasionally became a bit too much. I look forward to seeing much more of you both from now on.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
<pubDate>
Sat, 05 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0100
</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<guid>
http://clojuredatascience.com/posts/2015-04-07-hello-world.html
</guid>
<link>
http://clojuredatascience.com/posts/2015-04-07-hello-world.html
</link>
<title>
Hello, World!
</title>
<description>
&lt;p&gt;Welcome to the companion website for the book &lt;strong&gt;Clojure for Data Science&lt;/strong&gt;. The book is currently being written by &lt;a href='http://henrygarner.com'&gt;Henry Garner&lt;/a&gt; and will be published by &lt;a href='https://www.packtpub.com/'&gt;Packt&lt;/a&gt; in the second half of 2015.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;All code examples will be made available on the book's &lt;a href='https://github.com/clojuredatascience/'&gt;GitHub repo&lt;/a&gt; for download. As publication approaches this site (and the related &lt;a href='https://github.com/clojuredatascience/clojuredatascience.github.io/wiki'&gt;wiki&lt;/a&gt;) will be updated with excerpts and further information related to data science in general and Clojure in particular.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;See you soon.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
<pubDate>
Tue, 07 Apr 2015 00:00:00 +0100
</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
